Guide to the Charles A. Ellwood papers, 1889-1946 UA.29.02.0022
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles A. Ellwood papers
1889-1946
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ellwood, Charles A. (Charles Abram), 1873-1946
UA.29.02.0022
6.5 Linear Feet 14 boxes
Charles Abram Ellwood (1873-1946) established the Department of Sociology at Duke University in 1930, retiring in 1944. The papers feature incoming and outgoing correspondence, chiefly professional but with some personal exchanges; minutes and other records of Pi Gamma Mu; book and article manuscripts; speeches; news clippings and book reviews; and some photographs. There are some papers related to his teaching career, chiefly related to summer school appointments and his positions at Missouri and Duke. A microfilm copy of a scrapbook (circa 1900-1946) contains clippings from Ellwood's career. Professional topics in the papers cover discussion and criticism of Ellwood's books, articles, and views; international and U.S. sociology organizations; the sociology departments at the University of Missouri and Duke University; social ethics; criminology; the social function of religion; and the scientific and statistical approach to sociology. Issues in Ellwood's papers related to crises of the time include race relations; political systems and beliefs; Fascism; persecution of Jews in Europe; U.S. involvement in World War II; religion and ethics; militarism and pacifism; and compulsory conscription.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisitions Information
The papers were received as a transfer on April 11, 1973 (Accession number: 73-62).
Accession UA2019.0047 received as a gift, 2019.
Biographical Note
Charles Abram Ellwood established the Department of Sociology at Duke University in 1930. He was born in the rural community of Black Lake near Ogdensburg, New York, on January 20, 1873. Ellwood earned his bachelor's degree from Cornell University in 1896 and his Ph.D. from the University of Chicago. He married Ida Breckenridge in 1897. He continued his studies in Europe at the University of Berlin, Oxford University, and the University of London. Ellwood served as Head of the Department of Sociology at the University of Missouri and then moved to Duke University in 1930.
His numerous writings, such as Social Problems, a Sociology (1932) and The World's Need of Christ (1940), focus on social psychology, religion and ethics, social scientific methods, criminology, and the family. Heavily influenced by the work of Charles H. Cooley, Ellwood believed in social reform and human improvement through rational evolution, and was a supporter of eugenics to some degree. In 1912 or 1913, he gave a lecture at Missouri, "The Eugenics Movement from the Standpoint of Sociology," which was chosen as part of a book, Eugenics: Twelve University Lectures, published by the Dodd, Mead & Company in 1914.
Ellwood actively participated in several national and international organizations, inlcuding International Congress of Arts and Science, the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Sociological Society, Pi Gamma Mu National Social Science Honor Society, the International Congress of Sociology, and the National Education Association. He served as advisory editor of the American Journal of Sociology and as associate editor of the Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology. Ellwood retired from Duke University in 1944; he died in Durham, N.C., September 25, 1946.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sociologist Charles A. Ellwood feature incoming and outgoing correspondence, chiefly professional but with some personal exchanges; minutes and other records of Pi Gamma Mu; book and article manuscripts; speeches; news clippings and book reviews; and some photographs. There are some papers related to his teaching career, chiefly related to summer school appointments and his positions at University of Missouri--Columbia and Duke University. A microfilm copy of a scrapbook (circa 1900-1946) contains clippings from Ellwood's career. Professional topics in the papers cover discussion and criticism of Ellwood's books, articles, and views; international and U.S. sociology organizations; the sociology departments at the University of Missouri and Duke University; social ethics; criminology; the social function of religion; and the scientific and statistical approach to sociology. Issues in Ellwood's papers related to crises of the time include race relations; political systems and beliefs; Fascism; persecution of Jews in Europe; U.S. involvement in World War II; religion and ethics; militarism and pacifism; and compulsory conscription.
College teachers -- Correspondence; Criminology; Religion -- Study and teaching; Social psychology; Social sciences -- Methodology; Sociologists -- Correspondence; Sociology -- History -- 20th century; Sociology -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; Durham (N.C.) -- Intellectual life; North Carolina; Photographs; Scrapbooks; American Sociological Society; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Department of Sociology; Ellwood, Charles A. (Charles Abram), 1873-1946; Pi Gamma Mu
- Papers, circa 1889-1946
  Scope and Contents
  Folders contain background information on sociologist Charles H. Ellwood; correspondence files, chiefly professional with some family letters scattered through later years; some photographs; teaching materials; and a positive microfilm reel of Ellwood's scrapbook relating chiefly to his career. Correspondence is chiefly to and from colleagues, with many in European countries and in Japan. Some relate to publishing and service in organizations; others discuss sociological issues, often at length. Exchanges between long-time colleagues or former students are more personal, particularly as infirmities and losses come with advanced age.
  - Biographical information on Charles Ellwood and genealogy of Ellwood family, circa 1920-1944 (Box 1)
    Contains a 4-page typescript of "Circular issued by Brigadier General Isaac Ellwood on taking command of the 11th Brigade of New York State Infantry, April 4th, 1829." This is followed by several copies of Ellwood's resume`, list of publications, his autobiographical essay, with a few fragment pages attached, and several copies of a lengthy letter from an Ellwood cousin with a genealogy of various branches of the Ellwood family.
  - Bibliographies, 1937-1944 (Box 1)
    Chief item of interest is one 34-page soft-bound typescript bibliography of Ellwood's writings and writings about him, compiled in 1944 by Duke reference librarian MaryVie Cramblitt, with preface, introduction, and index. Also includes small group of loose sheets containing lists of publications by sociology faculty at Duke University, 1937-1941.
  - Correspondence, 1892-1923; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1933; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1936; 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1946; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and cards with no dates, circa 1920s-1944 (Box 5)
    Undated letters, Christmas cards, and postcards.
  - Photographs, 1910s-1930s (Box 5)
    Photographs of Ellwood residence and from travels. Also contains postcards. Locations include France, Monte-Carlo, Maine, and Sicily.
  - Teaching: Final Exams Soc. 102 and Anthro. - Duke University, 1935-1944 (Box 5)
  - Teaching: Summer School - Colorado, 1915-1924 (Box 5)
  - Teaching: Summer School - University of Southern California, 1923-1926 (Box 5)
  - Photograph: Panorama of large group of men and women on snowy slope, Ward, Colorado, 1917-06-01 (Box 6)
    Measures 12 3/4 x 5 1/4 inches. Written on back: "Taken June 30, 1917 on the twentieth anniversary of our marriage."
  - Sociology notebook with early reading or lecture notes, circa 1889 (Box 6)
    Hard-bound notebook labeled "Sociology" and underneath perhaps an instructor's name.
  - Scrapbook (microfilm on reel), circa 1900-1946 (Box 8)
    Positive microfilm of scrapbook assembled by Ellwood and chiefly containing clippings and other professional publicity. Negative copy may be available in Perkins Library microfilm collection.
- Printed Materials, 1890-1946
  A wide variety of professional materials that include programs, conference materials, cards, fliers, and articles and clippings by and about Charles Ellwood. Some of the paper is embrittled; please handle with care. Folder contents are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Certificates, publicity and programs, 1890-1946; 2 folders (Box 6)
    Begins with early education materials, including 1890 society yearbook from Ogdensburg Academy and Ellwood's 1890 graduation certificate. Subsequent materials include publicity about Ellwood's writings, short articles by Ellwood and others, clippings, letters to the editor, cards, tickets, and event programs. Arranged in rough chronological order. Oversize State Department passports and other certificates removed to oversize housing.
  - Diploma, travel documents, summer school poster, 1890-1927 (Box 14)
    Ogdenburg Academy graduation certificate and two State Department-issued travel documents, 1897 and 1914, one with Ellwood's photograph attached. Also includes summer school poster from the Colorado Agricultural College, 1927.
  - Certificates, publicity and programs, 1913-1946 (Box 7)
    Chiefly clipped articles, letters to the editor, program cards, publicity for Ellwood's publications, personal items such as insurance advertisement, and some certificates.
  - Early clippings, 1902-1930s (Box 7)
  - Clippings, 4 folders (Box 7)
    Many of these items speak to wartime concerns. Topics include morality and war; conscription; atomic power; integration; and socialism/cooperatives. Titles from which clippings were taken include: The Catholic Worker; Reporter; The New Leader; The Orphan's Friend and Masonic Journal; Congressional Record; Pi Gamma Mu; Independent Woman; Harvard University Gazette; The Italian Mail; The Llano Colonist; and The Nation. Not arranged in date order. Oversize items have been separated and rehoused.
  - Oversize clippings and articles, 1926-1940s (Box 14)
    Of note are issues from The New Leader, 1946; a newsletter from the Llano Cooperative in Louisiana (1926); and a broadside about conscription.
  - Poster on U.S. military conscription, 1947 or 1948 (Box 14)
    Poster questioning military draft includes statistics and quotes from Federal hearings. Measures approx. 17x22 inches.
  - Reprints, articles, journal Issues, 1902-1926; 2 folders (Box 8)
    Chiefly early reprints of Ellwood's writings, with some journal issues, mostly the Psychological Bulletin; also includes many essays and excerpts, and some programs. Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Articles, extracts, galleys, letters to the editor, 1906-1927 (Box 8)
    Early sociology pieces by Ellwood, including several original typescripts; there are also some galley proofs. Arranged in rough chronological order. Oversize materials have been separated and rehoused.
  - Letter to the editor, article, galley proofs, 1909, 1925 and undated (Box 14)
    Oversize materials include an issue of the serial The Nation, 1909, with letter to the editor by Ellwood; an article by Ellwood on family and religion, and undated galley proofs for encyclopedia entries on pauperism.
  - Reprints, articles, 1905-1930 (Box 9)
    Roughly 18 reprints of Ellwood's sociology writings, and some letters to the editor. Includes a 1910 issue of social reform publication The Survey with a photo of Harlem boy by Lewis Hine on the cover. Arranged in rough chronological order.
- Subject Files, 1900-1946
  Original order has been retained. Contains a wide variety of genres, chiefly short writings, mostly academic. Many reflect on significant issues of the day, including race, violence, religious and civil freedom, political society, pacifism, and war. Other folders document Ellwood's role in professional organizations. This series includes many of Ellwood's writings, most notably book reviews and letters to the editor; other pieces are found in the Writings series. Folder contents are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Abstracts, circa 1943 (Box 9)
    Several abstracts, one of which is from an edited work titled Social Forces, published in 1944.
  - American Sociological Society and Southern Sociology Society, 1920-1946 (Box 9)
  - Anthropology, 1918-1945 (Box 9)
    Academic articles, book chapters, and extensive lecture notes on anthropology. The earliest date appears to be a lecture notes from a course taught by Ellwood.
  - Biographies, 1920s (Box 9)
    Includes biography of Charles H. Cooley, one of Ellwood's mentors.
  - Book reviews (by Ellwood), 1904-1918 (Box 9)
    Drafts and finished pieces. The two earliest reviews, 1904 and 1905 deal with books on race and miscegenation by Thomas Nelson Page and William Benjamin Smith.
  - Book reviews (by Ellwood), 1920-1943; 2 folders (Box 10)
    Drafts and finished pieces.
  - Book reviews of Ellwood's writings, 1915-circa 1940 (Box 10)
    Several reviews appear in French and Italian journals.
  - Charity Organization Society, 1900-1945 (Box 10)
    Organization in Nebraska with which Ellwood was closely affiliated and served as Secretary.
  - Christianity and Social Science (1923) - reviews, 1920s (Box 10)
  - Criminology, 1907-1911 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous topics, 1901-1929 (Box 10)
    An assortment of writings by Ellwood, chiefly letters to the editor, small essays, some reviews, poems, and fliers for Ellwood's early lectures. A few are in German. Most of these materials date from his Missouri days. Of interest are two pieces on race: one is a 1945 declaration by the INTERdependence, Inc., of Los Angeles, "Racial Appreciation: a Practical Approach," a one-sheet detailed proposal for an emblem for businesses and non-profits who do not condone discrimination on the basis of "human pigmentation." The other is a public statement by Ellwood following a remark he made about lynching and its relation to a community's morals to a class on criminology. Oversize chart separated and rehoused.
  - Oversize manuscript chart mapping themes from Ratzenhofer's "Ideal Civilization", circa 1904 (Box 14)
    Measures approximately 12x17 inches.
  - N.C. Conference for Social Service, 1933-1934 (Box 10)
  - Pi Gamma Mu, 1932-1936 (Box 11)
    Chiefly reports, conference agendas, and bylaws.
  - Programs, 1901-1930 (Box 11)
  - Psychology of Human Society (1925), 1925 and undated (Box 11)
  - Religion, 1930-1946 (Box 11)
    Many of these relate to religious themes as they relate to the rise of Fascism, the plight of Jews, and violent conflicts of the period.
  - Reconstruction of Religion (1922), 1922-1924 (Box 11)
  - Scottish Rite Progress, 1925-1929 and undated (Box 11)
    Mostly pages from the Masons' newsletter containing articles by or about Ellwood.
  - Sociologist, 1945 and undated (Box 11)
    A folder of biographical sketches, a clipping from the Durham Herald newspaper, 1945, and reprints of Charles Ellwood, compiled by an unknown person, with a written inscription " My beloved major professor and friend - a world renown sociologist. His life and a few reprints."
  - University of Missouri, 1901-1930 (Box 11)
    Department handbook, syllabus of lectures, fliers and programs, and a few other items.
- Writings, 1896-1946
  Original order has been retained. Contains academic writings by Charles Ellwood in the form of chapter drafts, articles, editorials, lectures, and speeches, many with annotations, almost all relating to sociology and related academic topics. Many speak to significant issues of the day, including race relations, eugenics, and political society. Later pieces from the 1930s and early 1940s reflect the issues of totalitarianism, religious conflict, and war. This series includes many of Ellwood's writings, most notably book reviews and letters to the editor; other pieces are found in the Writings series. Folder contents are arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Conscription: Resistance, circa 1944-1946 (Box 11)
    Contains a cluster of editorials, articles, and an issue of "Conscription News," all related to Ellwood's stance against compulsory conscription.
  - Cultural Evolution (1927), circa 1927-1928 (Box 11)
    Complete annotated typescript and proofs draft, chapter abstracts, and review.
  - Cultural Evolution II, circa 1927 (Box 12)
  - Die Leuchte, 1925-1929 (Box 12)
    Issues of German journal and one issue of another title, containing references to Ellwood.
  - Duke, 1930s (Box 12)
    Writings chiefly related to the vision of the new Sociology Department, a proposal for a new Social Sciences Building, and publicity regarding new faculty. Includes a sociology lecture by Ellwood and readings list.
  - Duke Press, 1930s (Box 12)
    Introduction to a translation of Czech sociologist Chalupny's work, Dynamic Sociology.
  - Education, 1930s (Box 12)
    Various drafts of articles on the sociology of education and one on social studies in the classroom.
  - A History of Social Philosophy (1938), 1938 and undated (Box 12)
  - International Institute of Sociology, 1935-1937 (Box 12)
  - Introductions and editorials, 1935 (Box 12)
  - Introduction to Social Psychology (1917) - reviews, 1917-1919 (Box 12)
  - Man's Social Destiny (1930) - reviews, 1929-1930 (Box 12)
  - Marriage and the Family, 1925-1944 (Box 12)
  - Methods in Sociology (1933), 1930-1940 (Box 12)
    Complete or near-complete typescript draft, and drafts of related articles and reviews.
  - The Social Problem (1915) - reviews (Box 13)
  - Sociology - general articles, 1930s-1940s (Box 13)
    Mostly undated, but seem to be from the 1930s and 1940s. Includes a lecture or speech on "Evolutionary pacifism."
  - Speeches by Ellwood, 1898-1944 (Box 13)
    Presidential addresses, lectures, and various speeches. Includes his retirement speech at Duke. The earliest is titled "The marks of a sociological method that shall be adequate to construct a scientific basis for social control," written for Dr. Georg Simmel, the University of Berlin. One lecture from 1924 is on "Intolerance," and mentions the Ku Klux Klan. The last, "Valedictory," is Ellwood's retirement speech.
  - Thesis by Charles Ellwood, Cornell University: The relation of the social sciences to ethics: an historical study, 1896 (Box 13)
    Original manuscript copy.
  - The World's Need of Christ (1940), after 1940 (Box 13)
    Complete typescript draft, followed by several reviews.
  - World War II, 1924-circa 1944 (Box 13)
    Prefaced by several early pieces, some relating to the economic crises of the 1930s, including a revised draft of the Home Colonies Plan by Princess Lazarovich (born Eleanor Calhoun) submitted to President Roosevelt. There are materials from the Emergency Peace Campaign of 1936 and post-war peace efforts. There are a group of short editorials or lectures by Ellwood on the war, militarism, peace efforts, and totalitarianism. Also includes "Adjustment of the College Curriculum to Wartime Conditions and Needs, Report No. 3. Sociology," several pages with directions from the U.S. Office of Education, 1942.
  - Writings by Others: Autobiography by Charles H. Cooley, undated (Box 13)
    Cooley was an influential mentor to Charles Ellwood.